A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - 1910-1930 Correspondence: J-K, including Herbert W. Jackson; Dr. Walter B. James; William James (1842-1910) states that health concerns prevents him from lecturing at the University of Virginia (January 22, 1910); Dr. J.L. Jarman, President, State Teachers College, Farmville, Virginia, Alderman letter praising his work for a quarter century (May 5, 1927); letter from Alderman to Delegate Charles Thomas Jesse (1878-1960) about the importance of the State making an appropriation of $250,000 for the construction of medical school buildings at the University of Virginia in order to receive the gift of $700,000 promised by the General Education Board towards the same end (February 26, 1926); Walter A. Jessup, [President?] of the State University of Iowa (January 7, 1930); Alderman to C.T. Jordan concerning prohibition (July 1, 1909); J.Y. Joyner, North Carolina Superintendent of Public Instruction on the reception of his telegram being read at the unveiling of the Charles Duncan McIver statue (May 16, 1912); Frances Parkinson Keyes sends her article from Good Housekeeping concerning the University of Virginia's Centennial, not present (August 20, 1921); Alderman to Dr. E.A. Kincaid; Louis Kraus, Jr.; and Alderman to Mrs. James R. Kyle concerning the higher education of women (January 13, 1910) (Box-folder 4:1)
  - 1910-1931 Correspondence: Dr. Clara Ernull Jones (1847 -1934) (Mrs. William Joseph Jones), Goldsboro, North Carolina, friend of Alderman since 1882, periodic letters of friendship and concern and a letter of condolence in 1931 to Bessie Alderman (Box-folder 4:2)
  - 1903-1928 Correspondence: Jean Jules Jusserand (1855-1932), French Ambassador to the United States, concerning his speech at the University of Tulane (December 8, 1903) and the University of Virginia (November 11, 21, 1904); and the Lafayette Room (the French Room), Romance Pavilion, East Lawn, at the University of Virginia (June 10, 1928) (Box-folder 4:3)
  - 1900-1930 Correspondence: L, including: Justice J.R. Lamar (1857-1916); cards describing "Lambeth's Christmas Present, 1922"; Franklin Knight Lane, Secretary of the Interior; Dr. Burnley Lankford; William Laurence; Walter Lawrence; Sir Walter Lawrence, Royal Air Force; Bishop William Lawrence concerning the distribution of the remainder of the Peabody Fund (June 1, 1909); D.H. Leake, Chief of Staff, Governor's Office; Frank H. Leavell, editor of The Baptist Student, requesting an article from Alderman for the magazine (October 20, December 3, 1927); Fitzhugh Lee, President of the Jamestown Exposition Company; T. Bailey Lee, Idaho Supreme Court Justice, including some of his verses (April 17, 1930); Albert Lefevre; Benjamin Franklin Leggett; Alderman congratulates James Hamilton Lewis (1863-1939) on his election to the Senate and asks details about a story concerning his entrance into the University in 1883-1884 (November 5, 1930); Judge Benjamin Franklin Long; Alderman to Breckinridge Long; Samuel B. Love; Seth Low concerning Alderman's speech at the New England Society dinner (December 26, 1906); and A. Lawrence Lowell (Box-folder 4:4)
  - 1922-1925 Correspondence: Edmund Jones Lilly (1850-?), a friend of Alderman's from North Carolina days (Box-folder 4:5)
  - 1905-1931 Correspondence: Mc, including: W.G. McAdoo, telegram from William Gibbs McAdoo (1820-1894) about asking Alderman to speak at a Wilson-Marshall rally in Wilmington, North Carolina (n.d.) and a letter refusing an invitation to speak at the University of Virginia while expressing admiration for Alderman's tribute to Woodrow Wilson (August 9, 1912); A.W. McAlister tries to get Alderman to attend their 40 th Reunion [at Chapel Hill?] (June 2, 1922); W. Gordon McCabe thanks Alderman and remarks upon three of his speeches, recently received, including Virginia and mentions the military service of his son (March 20, 19198); Henry G. McCall concerning confusion over an invitation for Alderman to speak to University of Virginia alumni in New Orleans (February 11, 1931); Charles McClure; Alderman to W.F. McCombs, about Woodrow Wilson's candidacy for the presidency in Virginia (November 15, 1911); Lutie A. McCorkle, Alderman writes concerning his early religious life (January 30, 1930); Leander McCormick-Goodhart; Robert S. McCormick concerning Russia (October 27, 1905); Alderman to John A. McIlhenny; Alderman to Paul G. McIntire concerning the establishment of a School of Fine Arts at the University, beginning with a School of Art (March 4, 1919); Alderman to A.W. McLean discussing Nicholas Worth and its author, Walter Hines Page (October 19, 1919); and Charles S. McVeigh (Box-folder 4:6)
  - 1901-1906, n.d. Correspondence: Charles Duncan McIver (1860-1906), concerning the Southern Education Convention at Columbia and a SEC board meeting; and the Georgia Campaign fund (1906) (Box-folder 4:7)
  - 1901-1930 Correspondence: Ma through Mi, including Alderman letter to Dr. Hamilton W. Mabie, thanking him for his praise of Alderman's article in Outlook, referring to the new President Roosevelt and the death of President William McKinley, and the need for the education of both races in the South (September 24, 1901); [Alfred Thayer] Mahan (1840-1914); Dean John L. Manahan concerning the growth of elementary education in Virginia since 1890 (November 14, 1924); Charles G. Maphis; Theodore Marburg; Alderman suggests to Elisabeth Marbury an outline for a course on the South with suggested lecturers (March 24, 1910); Elizabeth G. Martin; Senator Thomas S. Martin responds to a petition from the faculty about the arbitration treaties currently before the Senate (December 5, 1911); and thanks Alderman for his sympathy at the death of his wife, Lucy Martin (January 27, 1915); [Thomas G. Masaryk]; Vincent Massey (1887-?), Canadian Legation, sends Alderman a novel by J.B. Priestley The Old Dark House and remarks on sharing a fondness for mysteries (May 23, 1928); Frank Mebane; Adelaide Meares; Messrs. Meister & Smethie Bookbinders; Alderman responds to criticisms from Wyndham R. Meredith about the University in the copy of his letter to Governor Davis discussing the New Co-ordinate College Bill (November 19, 1917); Alderman's statement concerning the second Liberty Loan for G.R.B. Michie (October 20, 1917); C.R. Miller, The New York Times, asks for a list of prominent Democratic men about whom sketches could be written (November 25, 1912); Dr. Edwin Mims asks Alderman for information to help him write his article in World's Work concerning the educational development of Virginia in the past five or six years (November 22, 1911) and writing a book on the life of Walter Hines Page (January 13, 1919); Raleigh Colston Minor (1869-1923) about his illness (April 25, 1923) and his wife, Natalie Venable Minor, about his death (November 1 & 7); and S. Weir Mitchell (Box-folder 4:8)
  - 1905-1930 Correspondence: Mo through Mu, including: Governor Andrew Jackson Montague (1862- 1937) about Alderman's speech on Southern leadership (February 13, 1905); Robert Walton Moore (1859-1941), at Alderman's request, he provides information and thoughts about the recovery of the South from the Civil War for Alderman to use in his speech "The Growing South," Carnegie Hall, New York City (February 25, 1908); Senator John T. Morgan agrees to answer any question about Dr. Curry (July 26, 1905); E.P. Moses concerning the estate of James W. Hearn (March 24, 1919); Mary C.B. Munford concerning the issue of the women's college for Virginia (November 17, 1913; January 13, 1916; and January 15, 1920; and Hopson Owen Murfee, Sr. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - 1925 December 5 Correspondence: Edwin Markham (1852-1940) one letter describing his excitement and preparations for writing his poem about Edgar Allan Poe, Our Israfel; in memory of Edgar Allan Poe [New York, E.R. Trott, 1925], written for The English Poetry Review contest offering a prize of $500.00 for the best poem on Poe and his pleasure that Alderman had presented it to the Library for preservation (Box-folder 4:10)
  - 1905, 1915, n.d. Correspondence: John Singleton Mosby, suggests they invite the President, Vice-President, and Cabinet to Alderman's inauguration (March 20, 1905); and thanks Alderman for the medal and address of the Faculty awarded to him (February 21, 1915); and autograph on a card (n.d.) originals transferred to the Vault (Box-folder 4:11)
  - 1903 Correspondence: Edgar Gardner Murphy (1869-1913), founder of the Southern Education Board, writes thanking Alderman for telling Murphy he would consider the presidency of the University of Virginia which he feels "is the key to the public school situation in the South" (June 25, 1903); and a letter from Murphy to the Board of Visitors recommending Alderman for the presidency of the University of Virginia (July 3, 1903) (Box-folder 4:12)
  - 1907-1950 Correspondence: N, O, P, Q, including: National Committee of the United States For the Restoration of the University of Louvain (December 9, 1918); National Unemployment League with "Facts and Figures re Business Depressions" (ca. August 9, 1930); Rogelio Navarro, Panama, sends his respects to Alderman and the University of Virginia through the first airmail ever carried from Panama to the United States by Charles A. Lindbergh (February 9, 1929); Robert B. Nelson; New Hanover Historical Commission concerning the erection of a highway memorial plaque honoring Alderman in Wilmington, North Carolina (January 17, 1950); Rose Standish Nichols; and Charles D. Norton, Vice Chairman of the Red Cross War Council (July 18, 1917); Robert C. Ogden (ca. 1909, December 7, 1912); John S. Patton (1857-1932), Librarian of the University, supplies information concerning the "Statute for Religious Freedom" for a proposed article by Alderman (February 1, 1924); Bruce R. Payne tells some amusing stories about his efforts at speaking in support of public education (January 20, 1930); Alderman to Judge John Barton Payne concerning the influence of H.L. Mencken (February 4, 1925) and asking for a donation to help construct some new alcoves in the renovated Art and Architecture Building, the old gymnasium, Fayerweather Hall (December 8, 1924); Colonel Oliver Hazard Payne; George L. Petrie concerning Alderman's transference of church membership from New Orleans to the Presbyterian Church in Charlottesville (September 25 1907); Alexander Lacy Phillips (1859- ) sends a letter of encouragement to Alderman reflecting upon all he has accomplished so far (February 27, 1913); Clarence Poe, President and Editor, The Progressive Farmer, including the issue of "pay as you go" versus the use of bond issues to pay for education (November 3, 1923); Frank Lyon Polk (1871-1943); T.C. Powell sends a photograph of Tulane University showing the oaks in Audubon Park (present, May 12, 1919); Robert Marshall Price (1881-1941), Miami Bank and Trust Company; Alderman to Nicholls Pugh reporting on the participation of the University of Virginia in the War (October 29, 1918); and Alderman to Fred H. Quarles, Jr. critiquing the report of the Omicron Delta Kappa Fraternity on why so many first year students fail their classes (May 11, 1927) (Box-folder 4:13)
  - 1929-1931 Correspondence: New York University Hall of Fame, Alderman was on the Committee of Nominations (Box-folder 4:14)
  - 1896-1931 Correspondence: Marcus Cicero Stephens Noble (1855-1941), professor and Dean of Education at the University of North Carolina; Alderman writes a very detailed letter to his old friend describing his stay at Saranac Lake, New York, for a tuberculosis cure and his determination to beat the dread disease (January 2, 1913); the need for more state funding if the University of North Carolina is to continue to grow (January 11, 1915); Noble's long career in education and his need for a pension (January 3, [1929]); the condition of George Winston (November 23, 1929); writes about his book on education and asks Alderman which photograph of himself he would like used in the book (August 7 and October 31, 1930; January 8, 1931) (Box-folder 4:15)
  - 1903-1922 Correspondence: Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922), answers Alderman's question about what the South had contributed to the life of the nation (May 28, 1903); urges Alderman to accept the presidency at the University of Virginia by telegram (June 15, 1904); Alderman addresses the false rumors that the serpentine walls at the University were to be removed and the standards for entrance into the University have been lowered (January 9, 1907); proposal from Secretary of the Interior Fisher that Alderman be made U.S. Commissioner of Education (June 3, 1911); thanks Alderman for recommending him to President Wilson for a diplomatic post and remarks upon current Virginia politics (March 24, 1913); plans to attend the University's Centennial events and refers to the Page-Barbour lectures endowed by his wife [Florence Lathrop Field] (1858-1921) and the Paul Goodloe McIntire gifts (May 10, 11, 1921); the sudden death of Page's wife [Florence Lathrop Field] (June 20, 1921); thanks Alderman for being one of the 150 recipients of the Centennial medals from the University (August 8, 1921); the invitation to deliver the upcoming Page-Barbour lectures (October 3, 6, 1921); accepts the appointment as a member of the Board of Trustees of the University Endowment Fund and decides on the lecture topic "Dante and His Time" for the Page-Barbour lectures (November 7, 16, 1921); and is unable to attend the next meeting of the Board of Trustees of the University Endowment Fund (July 10, 1922) (Box-folder 4:16)
  - [1899?], 1904-1919 Correspondence: Walter Hines Page (1855-1918), on The Atlantic Monthly stationery (Page was editor, 1898-1899) answers Alderman's question about the problem of liberalization of thought in North Carolina and methods of changing attitudes to the outside world, particularly through the teaching of history and economics, and Page's belief that the influence of "Dead Men's Hands" or dead opinions lies too heavily upon the people, "the weight of these mighty and invisible powers of the past - the dead part of the past, not the part that ought to live & be revered." ([1899?], this letter has the date August 21, 1896, on the top of page 1 but it is struck through); congratulates Alderman upon his marriage and promises to send copies of the first editions of three books by "the foremost woman now writing fiction in our language" unnamed by Page (February 9, 1904); also congratulates Alderman on becoming the President of the University of Virginia and urges him not to hesitate but "Where Jefferson laid the foundations, go, you, & build, if you have a building chance. Neither hesitate to be bold - very bold." He also emphasizes the influence of Jefferson upon freedom in his time (June 22, 1904); urges him to accept an offer from an university in St. Louis (May 31, 1907); wants to publish Alderman's Civic Forum speech in the World's Work (March 9, 11, 1908); in a letter to Bessie Alderman, Page asks how he can serve Alderman in his enforced isolation at Saranac Lake, New York, while recovering from tuberculosis (December 9, 1912); mentions his impression of Woodrow Wilson as President and [Frederick Taylor?] Gates, advisor to John D. Rockefeller, who was developing 17,000 acres of land in North Carolina and who said "he had left old Jno. D. for good" (December 9, 1912); shares his hopes and fears for the Woodrow Wilson presidency, and writes "but when this awful office descends on a man, it oppresses him, changes him, you are not quite as sure of him, you doubt whether he knows himself or you in the old way" (December 31, 1912); sends affectionate greetings on behalf of the Southern Education Board members, particularly mentions Robert C. Ogden in his final stages of illness, as Page reflects upon Ogden's involvement on the Board; he also praises the work of Wicliffe Rose and his work on the eradication of hookworm disease (January 26, 1913); mentions work on his farm in North Carolina and shares his reassurance in government with the election of Wilson, "I have a stronger confidence in government now as an instrument of human progress than I have ever had before." (March 10, 1913); reveals that President Wilson has appointed him as Ambassador to England (March 27, 1913); apologizes that he was unable to go and see Alderman before sailing for his post in England (May 19, 1913); Page's perspective on the relationship between England and the United States (Christmas 1913); Page arranges for the Aldermans to visit the home of Shakespeare's daughter, Susannah Hall, in Stratford (September 22, 1914); Alderman writes concerning the Lusitania matter (May 12, 1915); writes a very personal and revealing letter about his service as Ambassador to England during World War I, "what the continent has already become - a bankrupt slaughter-house inhabited by unmated women. We have talked of 'problems' in our day. We never had a problem; for the worst task we ever saw was a mere blithe pastime compared with what these women and the few men that will remain here must face. The hills about Verdun are not blown to pieces worse than the whole social structure and intellectual and spiritual life of Europe. I wonder that anybody is sane." Page believes the only answer is for the English-speaking men to work together to keep the predatory peoples at bay, to exchange students between the universities of the United States and Great Britain, casting aside the medieval traditions of the English colleges, and to lead the rest of the world into democracy and peace (June 22, 1916); has met Alderman's "Professor of Law in khaki" (December 31, 1917); a thank you note from the wife of Walter Hines Page, Alice, for Alderman's memorial speech about her husband upon his death (April 28, 1919); and a postcard of a memorial tablet honoring Page in Westminster Abbey for being Ambassador to Britain "in her sorest need" (n.d.) (Box-folder 4:17)
  - 1902-1932 Correspondence: George Foster Peabody (1852-1938), approves the action of the Mississippi Legislature and looks forward to hearing Alderman at Carnegie Hall (February 4, 1902); working to find a Rector at Holy Trinity and trying to get the assistant Head Master of the Groton School, Massachusetts, the Reverend Sherrard Billings (October 28, 1903); enjoyment of Alderman's speeches (May 4, 1905; February 25, 1908; and reading the Memorial speech for Mr. Shepard, May 14, 1912); refers to the poet, Mrs. Trask (May 14, 1912; February 23, 1913; January 30, 1914); Alderman thanks Peabody for sending him a copy of "President Wilson's War Mind" by Professor L.B. Jacks and comments upon the war leadership by Woodrow Wilson (October 7, 1918); announces his upcoming marriage to Katrina Trask (January 1921); and a note to Mrs. Alderman, in response to her New Year's greeting (August 1, 1932) (Box-folder 4:18)
  - 1903-1922 Correspondence: Henry Smith Pritchett (1857-1939), President of Massachusetts Institute of Technology and President of the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, expresses his pleasure at Alderman's acceptance of the presidency of the University of Virginia (August 1, 1904); Alderman to Pritchett sending documents and pamphlets to present the relations of the University to the Carnegie Foundation (October 28, 1905; April 28, 1910) and concerning the retiring allowance of Professor Harrison, Pritchett's letter to President George H. Denny about Washington and Lee University, and the re-making of the Medical School at the University of Virginia (June 12, 1909); and a letter from Alderman concerning the need for building construction and equipment for the Medical School of the University of Virginia (May 17, 1922) (Box-folder 4:19)
  - 1904-1930 Correspondence: R, including: Whitelaw Reid (1837-1912); Ira Remsen; William Gorham Rice; Carrie W. Richardson, [secretary?] to Alderman; Mrs. Lida B. Robertson (June 30, 1930); Alderman letter to Charles Rosen (1872-?) concerning his difficult decision to resign the presidency of the University of Tulane for that of the University of Virginia (July 7, 1904); E.C. Routh requesting a copy of Alderman's Woodrow Wilson memorial address (June 2, 1930); and J.M. Rowland, Editor of the Richmond Christian Advocate, requesting a statement from Alderman concerning the benefits of Prohibition at the University of Virginia (October 8, 1930) (Box-folder 5:1)
  - 1905-1929 Correspondence: Rockefeller Family, including John D. Rockefeller, Sr. (1839-1937), John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960) and Abby Rockefeller (1874-1948), Alderman writes asking for financial assistance for a listed group of needs at the University of Virginia (March 23, 1905); Alderman's draft of the acknowledgement of the General Education Board to John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s gift of 32 million dollars of securities (February 7, 1907); Rockefeller's plan to eradicate hookworm disease (October 26, 1909); their work to help the Belgian sufferers (November 24, 1914); their purpose that the various board members, "those responsible for the use of funds which my father has established may have the fullest freedom in the discharge of their duties from decade to decade, is Father's earnest desire and purpose, in which position I cordially concur" (August 25, 1926); his appreciation of Alderman's service on the General Education Board (January 1, 1929); the visit of the John D. Rockefeller, Jr. family to the University of Virginia (June 13, 19, 20, 1929; July 24, 26, 1929); and a photograph of [John D. Rockefeller, Sr.?] (Box-folder 5:2)
  - 1930-1936 Correspondence: President Franklin D. Roosevelt (1882-1945), concerning his visit to the Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Virginia (March 25, May 6, 1931); and social notes to Mrs. Alderman (1932-1936), originals transferred to Vault (Box-folder 5:3)
  - 1901-1911 Correspondence: President Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919), including chiefly social notes about meetings and visits, particularly one about "certain things connected to the South" (December 19, 1904); a letter stating that Roosevelt has "accepted in their substance, though with some change of form, your suggestions, excepting that about Lincoln's warring to free the slave" which he goes on to explain why, presumably for Roosevelt's speech at the Lincoln dinner of the Republican Club, New York City on February 13 th (January 17, 1905); a request for recommendations for members of a Referee Board to help enforce the Pure Food and Drug Act (January 16, 1908); asks Alderman about Judge Mears and Judge Timberlake in regards to an appointment that must be filled (December 29, 1908 and January 2, 1909) originals transferred to Vault (Box-folder 5:4)
  - 1905-1926 Correspondence: Senator Elihu Root (1845-1937), writes that he is unable to make his speech on Founder's Day due to illness (April 7, 1910); and sends a copy of his speech (not present) delivered at the unveiling of the Lincoln Statue in London (January 29, 1921) (Box-folder 5:5)